[SPEAKER_01]: Today, Buddhistor has the honor of interviewing his eminents, Shachenra Rinpoche and Ven.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matthew Ricard, who are on a visit to Hong Kong.
[SPEAKER_02]: The two masters will share their wisdom on topics including the relevance of Buddhism in the modern world, and the role of root gurus in Tibetan Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: So every student must get a root guru, is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, if you are going to sell in the ocean, you need to have a good captain to guide you.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, a spiritual master is a very good captain to help you navigate across the ocean.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I say you must have, in order to achieve enlightenment in Buddhahood, you must have a good spiritual master.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but actually, what is the true meaning of the root guru?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the difference between guru and root guru?
[SPEAKER_04]: Guru means something, Sanskrit word like guru means something like very heavy or very, in a sense I think what it means like if you know how to, first you find a right spiritual guru and if you know how to relate then that's the, the blessing is like very heavy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then if you, let's say,
[SPEAKER_04]: If you find an authentic spiritual guru and then you don't follow properly, then the consequence can be very heavy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Therefore, guru word means something very heavy.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I think, like I mentioned earlier, they can be like sutrayana, gurus, and then you can have mahayana.
[SPEAKER_04]: We will take bodhisattva vows and all that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, I think the more deeper connection
[SPEAKER_04]: with the guru, is the one who brings you into the Vajrayana path.
[SPEAKER_04]: And especially the one who actually, especially in our Nima tradition, the one who actually introduces you to the nature of your mind, we consider as the root guru.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: But can what guru be found so easily?
[SPEAKER_02]: Just by asking one Rinpoche, can you be my what guru, then he can become my what guru?
[SPEAKER_04]: I think there's lots of teaching how to relate with the master, analyzing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't mean again you go and dig up all their faults.
[SPEAKER_04]: But to see that, is this the right Guru, first of all knowing that he is the authentic Guru.
[SPEAKER_04]: And these days maybe sometime you can also Google it, get more information.
[SPEAKER_04]: But of course, I think
[SPEAKER_04]: I think the special quality of the Vajrayana Buddhist tradition is this authentic lineage.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, on that you can do some research, not just rely on flyers these days.
[SPEAKER_04]: Flyers, advertisements, go around saying, you know, I'm so-and-so, but I think it's quite easy to do a little bit further research, this lineage and authenticity.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then once you feel that this is the right, feel close connection, there are many cases some people like when they see or when they hear about the name of the Guru, then they really feel inspired and connected.
[SPEAKER_04]: In some cases it doesn't happen, but then you can, once you know it is the authentic Guru, then you can develop this kind of connection through many different ways, especially like practicing Guru Yoga as the way to connect to the Guru.
[SPEAKER_02]: Another talk you are going to have in Hong Kong is about happiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unfortunately, some Buddhists found they didn't become happier after learning about Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: They didn't become happier after learning Buddhism, or even they experienced more sadness, attachment and negative emotions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you heard about that situation?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you practice properly,
[SPEAKER_04]: I think the right way properly, then I think it should bring you temporary and ultimate happiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Temporary happiness, I think we can say that the whole teaching of Buddhists is based on how to deal with your negative emotion which causes all the sufferings and pains.
[SPEAKER_04]: So if you are practicing properly and if you are actually learning how to deal with your negative emotions which causes all the sufferings, then you should be a happier.
[SPEAKER_04]: And ultimate happiness is enlightenment Buddhahood.
[SPEAKER_04]: So if you don't do it properly then maybe you have a different result.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you give advice on how to learn Buddhism properly?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think we have to not lose the goal why we entered Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't join any religion thinking that it will bring you suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're looking for some kind of way to achieve happiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how you choose to
[SPEAKER_04]: follow our religion.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, same thing without losing our goal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Again and again reminding us why we joined to practice the Buddha Dharma and our goal is to achieve happiness temporarily and ultimately.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nowadays, many Chinese Buddhists are learning Tibetan Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: But many of them just emphasize empowerment, mantra and blessing, emphasize this very much, but seldom study the theory.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you have any advice for them?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, I think in order to become Vajrayana Buddhist practice, you must go through the receiving Abhisheka or empowerment.
[SPEAKER_04]: But again, like I mentioned before, I think it's very important to not only get the empowerment, but if you really want to be a good practitioner, then you have to follow in practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: But also there is kind of a tradition in Tibet where this Vajrayana is flourish, where people take empowerment just as a connection, to have a connection with spiritual master or lineage.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's another case.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you really want to seriously go into practice, then receive the initiation and then go into the practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's how you get into the Vajrayana path.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do they have to learn something or just by practice by chanting mantra, receiving empowerment?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think it's always necessary to learn how to practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also the chanting mantra is also not just a kind of saying by mouth, but you have to visualisation and there's lots of things deal with your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not just reciting mantra.
[SPEAKER_04]: We have a saying that
[SPEAKER_04]: reciting mantra without thinking is like a pirate reciting mantra.
[SPEAKER_04]: In Tibetan we say, nesomani.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, more is to do with your inner mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Many Chinese Buddhist emphasize empowerment, mandala and blessing very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think they don't think stopping the evil deed, practice, good deed, and holding the samaya vow is important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even they don't know after receiving empowerment they have to hold the Samayamao.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't know what Samayamao is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I want to ask for more advice from your immigrants for them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so when you receive the empowerment of Abhisheka, like in Tibet or where they practice Vajrayana Buddhists, there are many different ways of receiving empowerment.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some, like I mentioned before, they just make a connection and just to have a spiritual connection or to the lineage.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's just thinking like a blessing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then some want to engage more into that lineage and practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there they take the empowerment more seriously.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then they will have to... Well essence of the Vajrayana Samaya is to develop pure vision and devotion.
[SPEAKER_04]: So if that I think goes for all the Vajrayana practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I think people who
[SPEAKER_04]: do practice Vajrayana.
[SPEAKER_04]: Vajrayana, so they, more or less, they know, they should know the developing pure vision and devotion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is this the crucial, crucial essence?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Essence.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, that is for the base of Buddhism, not necessarily for Vajrayana.
[SPEAKER_04]: Base of Buddhism, first believing in the law of cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_04]: The essence of Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then rangisim ni yongsudul then comes different methods.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the quote that Rinpoche mentioned is, don't do any evil acts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Perform all virtues to transform what's mind as the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's what Rinpoche says, the basic quote of Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm afraid many Chinese Buddhists practice the lack of this basic knowledge.
[SPEAKER_04]: So also when you talk about the Dikpa and Gya-va, positive and negative version, also in Buddhism it's more on your intention, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Sambha-sambha.
[SPEAKER_04]: So intention directs towards positive or negative outcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much for Rinpoche's teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Toji-che used to be engaged very well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks a lot.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then it's my turn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, it's my partner's turn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable, thank you so much for being with us here today.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the advertisement of the talk, Buddhism and its relevance to the modern world, which is the second of the two talks, will be given on the 12th of September.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was declared, Buddhism is a pragmatic science of mind, an altruistic art of living, a meaningful philosophy,
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you explain how Buddhism can be science, art and philosophy all at the same time?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, science means honest, rigorous investigation of reality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now that's the criteria of good science, not based on blind faith, not based on hearsay, not based on hypothesis, which either have not been verified or cannot be verified.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might postulate something that you can never fully verified.
[SPEAKER_03]: So science has to be demonstrated on the base on empirical experience of data.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now the domain of science can vary.
[SPEAKER_03]: The modern science, basically the domain is what is measurable in the outside world.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is like biology, physics, and with mathematical laws.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we could say here, Buddhism as well as psychology and cognitive science is about science of mind, science of emotions, science of happiness and suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the process has to be as rigorous as it can.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means make hypotheses.
[SPEAKER_03]: For instance, there's ego grasping and boosting self-esteem going to make you happy or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can examine that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you can examine that with your own experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can examine that to psychological investigation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the answer is no.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it was yes, we said go for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Boost your ego as much as you can and see the result.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does jealousy help for happiness?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, try for 24 hours to be jealous from morning to evening, and if the result is good, go for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it's not, don't shoot yourself in the feet.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in that way is science.
[SPEAKER_03]: basically of how the mind works and how the mind can make us can be our best friend or worst enemy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now an art, in a way art means to someone who is very expert at certain art can skillfully perform his or her own art.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in a way, we speak of art of happiness, art of meditation, in the sense of a Buddhist heart, in the sense of doing properly, skillfully, in the best possible way, traveling on the path.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now philosophy, because it is not based only on sort of blind experience, but also it is guided by a view.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddhist view is crucial, especially when we deal with suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because one of the biggest misunderstanding about Buddhism and also one of the most profound teachings of the Buddha is that when we speak of suffering, it's not just to take our inconvenience and sorrows that you have momentarily, because everyone knows it is suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: When the Buddha said the truth of suffering, he doesn't have to say that
[SPEAKER_03]: A two-take is suffering, because everyone knows why we don't need the Buddha for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: What the Buddha said is suffering as a much deeper level than that, linked with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: That we don't usually recognize as suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the problem, because as long as we think that this kind of suffering that is guided by ignorance, by the mental toxins, and anger, and hatred, and greed, and desire, and so forth,
[SPEAKER_03]: is going to bring us happiness and if we enjoy temporary happiness, we think it's ultimate happiness, that ignorance is in a way suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that we don't know and we don't recognize.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in that sense, a philosophy in the sense of a view about what is the nature of reality, what is the nature of the self, what is the nature of phenomena,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's crucial in order to put things into practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, without that view, then there's no such thing as the Four Noble Truth.
[SPEAKER_03]: So to recognize the root as being ignorance and the freedom coming from wisdom and that there is a possibility to put an end to suffering, there are cause to suffering, there's a part.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's we could call a philosophy in terms of the maybe the word in Sanskrit darshan, which is a view about reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Buddhism as science, art, and philosophy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I realize that nowhere in there, in those three words, or in those four words, is mentioned religion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now as Buddhists, even if we don't try to actively convince other people to become Buddhists, we always hope to benefit them in some way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nowadays, as you probably well know, there are many who have given up on religion altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: not just their traditional religions but also simply about the idea of religion altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: So do you think we can present Buddhist theory and practice as what we've just discussed as free words of philosophy, art and science in order to benefit those people who have simply, frankly speaking, no interest or have given up?
[SPEAKER_03]: The idea of science, art and philosophy, we don't find that in scriptures and all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, if we say Buddhism is a sense of mind, I think that's a more concise definition.
[SPEAKER_03]: And of course, there are philosophical aspects, there are devotional aspects, there are many different aspects.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it is a way of transforming the mind from a state of ignorance and suffering to a state of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that, I think, would be completely fine in traditional perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, religion is all depends what you mean by that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, as it's honest, the Dalai Lama often says, there are taste religions.
[SPEAKER_03]: another three main religions of the book, like Christianity, Judaism, and Islam, believing a creator and a god.
[SPEAKER_03]: So he said there was a non-tastic religion like Buddhism and Jainism, which based their teaching on interdependence and law cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it means they're beginning less universe, and everything is ruled by the law of cause and effect, including happiness and suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you are your own creator, the diagram often says.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you could call it religion in the sense that there are practices that looks like, you know, religious, but they're also imbued all with meaning.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's never a notion of blind faith comes nowhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to make a leap of faith that you must believe into something that you can never verify.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's against Buddhism principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha always said, don't accept what I said just because I mentioned it, but examine it by yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you have to, step by step, being able to recognize the truth of the Buddha's suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So this being said now, as, again, it's not that Dalai Lama often says, more than half roughly of the humanity is either not, doesn't belong to any religion, is against religion, or is nominally religious, but don't do any practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: So he said, although the great religion about major contribution to the world,
[SPEAKER_03]: It will be a pity if some of the basic, most indispensable human values like compassion and altruism and happiness
[SPEAKER_03]: When you speak of compassion, people say, oh, that's for religious people.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not interested because I'm not religious.
[SPEAKER_03]: So he said, religion is a choice that we can make or do not make.
[SPEAKER_03]: But compassion is need, not this choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: We need it from the day we born.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, with this unidentified crying object that we call a baby, is no way to survive without the compassion of the mother, the father, those around the community.
[SPEAKER_03]: And elderly person also cannot survive without help.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in all the steps of our life, we need to receive and give compassion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's not linked with religion.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is a must for humanity.
[SPEAKER_03]: So therefore, he said, it would be a pity to equate compassion with religion.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why he promotes this idea of basic human values and secular ethics.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a diminished religion.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just to make sure that those basic values can be practiced by all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, if you use, like Buddhist teaching, you can enhance that and cultivate those much further.
[SPEAKER_03]: So there are tools to do that, but it's not indispensable, but at least we should recognize that those are basic values that everyone needs.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you want to cultivate them through religion, that's fine, it's up to you, but we should not just exclude the secular people from the idea of becoming a better human being.
[SPEAKER_01]: In your travels, have you noticed any differences between traditional Tibetan Buddhism and Tibetan Buddhism as practiced in Western regions?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, there are many different ways that is being done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Some are very authentic, traditional, as Karimshamusha said, based on authentic lineage.
[SPEAKER_03]: and by hairs of that lineage will do their best to preserve that authenticity and then to transmit the teaching in a correct way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's happening in the West, that's happening in the East.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there are also people who invent their own sort of fabrications and mix a little bit with that and this.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm often said I'm making kind of salad, mixed salad.
[SPEAKER_03]: So of course then it may not be so authentic.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's also happening in the East.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's not just for the West.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, even in Bonn, you know, sometimes it happens even with young Tibetan tisha that come out of nowhere, somewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you know, so that's why, as Sambri Moshe said, we need to examine according to the scriptures.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are many scriptures like the way of the great perfection of Patrice Moshe, and the treasury of precious quality of Jimi Limba, that explain in detail the characteristic of authentic teacher with ambience, with compassion, with wisdom, with knowledge of the scripture, with experience in the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this they wish from the fake teachers.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think many, many examples like fake teachers like a wooden mill, you know, wooden mill makes a lot of noise but doesn't make the grain become flour.
[SPEAKER_03]: So make a lot of noise by speaking but doesn't change the disciples, sort of transform the disciples' nature.
[SPEAKER_03]: So whatever is east or west, that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_03]: Traditionally, we used for many years, to 12 years, we're supposed to make sure that we rely on an authentic teacher.
[SPEAKER_03]: Likewise, the teacher also should examine the disciple if someone was committed, who has determination, who has confidence, who can perseverance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So they're mutually examining each other before committing oneself and not jumping into anybody that comes and advertises, as Yamushi says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tell me about your work with Karuna Shetchan.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's so much this charity does, from initiatives to empower women, to invest them in sanitation in East Tibet, and training students in India to do solar power.
[SPEAKER_01]: What parts are you involved with?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there are two aspects of activities of the room machine that I try to serve.
[SPEAKER_03]: One is purely spiritual, to preserve the tradition, to restoring monasteries, like we are trying to rebuild the session monastery in Tibet and the monastery colleges and retreat centers and being monks and nuns.
[SPEAKER_03]: in different parts of the world, like in Tibet, Bhutan, and Nepal, India, and so to preserve the tradition.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's the core of the mission of the Kansai Moshe's lineage.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now it's also the activity aspect of compassionate activity that is an outcome of the Dharma and that is meant to address as much as we can any suffering that we encounter.
[SPEAKER_03]: So of course we cannot do everywhere in the world everything at the same time so we are not don't have any karma possibly to do that somewhere in Africa or somewhere because of our
[SPEAKER_03]: personal sort of connections.
[SPEAKER_03]: It happens that we are living in those four countries I mentioned and therefore that's where we try our best to put compassion in action through those activities.
[SPEAKER_03]: So over 10 years and the first long-term ago cancer machine inspiration and jumping machine inspiration since 2000
[SPEAKER_03]: We accomplished almost 110 projects in health and education, mostly dispensaries, clinics and schools, as well as social work like helping the elderly, the orphans.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is an outcome of the Dharma.
[SPEAKER_03]: to serve as much as we can, people who are in need in the areas that we know well, and we speak the language when we have connections.
[SPEAKER_03]: And sometimes, thanks to the spiritual connection, we can work better.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's our dedication.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also, because of the
[SPEAKER_03]: dedicated to the people, grassroots, and in a secular way because we are not trying, you know, covertly to promote religion to that, but just helping people who need, and so also it can be joined by people who have sinned but if are Buddhism but are not necessarily Buddhists themselves.
[SPEAKER_03]: So which is the case, we just want to do charitable work.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are stopping first in Hong Kong and then in Singapore and then Mexico.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can all tell what's the odd one out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so why Mexico?
[SPEAKER_01]: And how do you see the development of Buddhism in Latin America?
[SPEAKER_03]: So we're not going to probably try to solve the drug problem in Mexico and the gangs and all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hope would survive.
[SPEAKER_03]: But basically, you know,
[SPEAKER_03]: that shows that the Buddha Dharma has taken roots in many places and actually this very enthusiastic community in Mexico and they are very naturally enthusiastic people, like you know, legends people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even in Europe, the people from the South like Portugal and Spain and Italy, they are more showing outer enthusiasm
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I think for many years in Mexico there have been a lot of people very keen to study Buddhism and Tibetan Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, since we have personal connections and now a small session center was established at the request of the Mexican people.
[SPEAKER_03]: And Jemboche goes from time to every few years and we have also
[SPEAKER_03]: teacher who graduated from a more philosophical college in Nepal who is now residing there and just trying to help people who want to study the Buddha Dharma to do it in a proper way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our modern world has been irrevocably changed by social media.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, many who will be listening to you talk are parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they are very curious and very interested to know what to do about their kids who are constantly on social media and on all these new platforms that have transformed the way we socially interact online and in person.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you see the role of Buddhism or Buddhist teachings in advising those parents on how they can relate to their children and advise them?
[SPEAKER_04]: The social media is very powerful.
[SPEAKER_04]: It has a positive negative negative.
[SPEAKER_04]: The social media is very positive.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like any powerful tools, a tool can be used in positive and negative ways.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hammer, you can destroy a house or build a house.
[SPEAKER_03]: For likewise, obviously social media is a powerful tool of communication, of linking people together that can be used for good, that can be used for either negative things or even just simply to waste one's human life in time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Time is one of the most precious things we have and people underestimate the value of time.
[SPEAKER_03]: They think that they won't ask you for your watch, but they will ask you for three hours of your time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Probably the most precious three hours of life than you watch anyway.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's a consideration that the parents should have, not just pulling the plug.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's quite upset.
[SPEAKER_03]: But so it is difficult to make sure that this is used for the right purpose.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in a way you can see that in any case it has been used to promote wonderful causes like democracy and things, to promote knowledge.
[SPEAKER_03]: So all the tools for good are there.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's also a negative effect, obviously.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the negative effect, the studies of psychologists have shown that the biggest risk is to just increase narcissism, boosting this kind of self-esteem that's finding a window to show off when nobody else will listen to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also it makes the conversation very poor.
[SPEAKER_03]: Imagine you have 3,000 friends on MySpace of Facebook,
[SPEAKER_03]: If you don't have a conversation with 3,000 people, you just expose yourself as again and again and again.
[SPEAKER_03]: So especially in the United States, there has been a psychological study showing that if you ask kids,
[SPEAKER_03]: or a teenager or anyone actually, even adult, to spend 30 minutes updating their MySpace or Facebook page.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you ask them to do 30 minutes of looking for information on something on the internet or like a Google map or something, and then you measure their level of narcissism with a questionnaire, after 30 minutes, there's a significant increase of narcissistic
[SPEAKER_03]: you know, ego-centered attitude even after 30 minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that shows that it is, that danger is one of the strongest dangers because that promotes wild individualism, which is the last thing we need, which is increasing a lot in certain countries, much less in the East so far, but it's coming.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's the main danger, because there's nothing that can replace a real conversation between human beings.
[SPEAKER_03]: Conversation, you can judge people's facial emotions, you can feel, you can change the course of the conversation as you interact.
[SPEAKER_03]: but this virtual interaction can be very brutal and sometimes used also to demean people and can be very cruel.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are many cases of suicides following, bullying, virtual bullying.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that aspect of dehumanizing human relations is somehow dangerous.
[SPEAKER_03]: So how to control that?
[SPEAKER_03]: I think parents need to give quality time to their children, to themselves, take them to places where there is really something wonderful happening, to their visits, something to travel or even to spend time.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have a friend who has been studying consumerism and he said, I met him in a conference in Bangkok on Buddhism and consumerism.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said he spent the morning in a park in Bangkok with his son.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was a wonderful time watching some statues and flowers, exotic flowers and birds.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he said, and father and son together, they had such a wonderful time.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, that would have taken my son to a supermarket.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we'd have both things that we don't need.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then we'd have taken maybe a tuk-tuk, like a rickshaw, and then we might have an accident, and then a court case, and then taking the rickshaw driver to hospital.
[SPEAKER_03]: All that would be much better for the consumption and the economy, but it would be much less in terms of human relations.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I think, in general,
[SPEAKER_03]: We should be very worried about, we should encourage really warm, fulfilling, enriching human relationship and those tools can be very useful for doing research, for writing useful things.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can also be a terrible tool of distraction and especially the violent video games.
[SPEAKER_03]: absolutely well established without controversy that the increase violent attitudes and violence behavior this this is not matter anymore of discussion this is entirely clear and and it has not only a short term effect of increasing aggressive behavior following
[SPEAKER_03]: playing a violent game, but it has a cumulative effect and you can measure it down five years later.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is really something that is destructive to making a compassionate person.
[SPEAKER_04]: crime rate higher than TV 10 crime rate.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also the television is the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that television is bad per se, but television has a totally unnatural amount of violent images.
[SPEAKER_03]: By 12 years old, an European and American boy or girl have seen 12,000 crimes on TV.
[SPEAKER_03]: So basically, even program for children, 70% of violent images, about 14 per hour, was just looking at the statistic.
[SPEAKER_03]: That means at the end of the year, you have seen tens of thousands of violent acts.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is totally unreal.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is nothing to do with real life.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, fortunately, it's quite rare that a teenager has seen a real murder in real life.
[SPEAKER_03]: But he has seen 20,000 by 20 years old.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's given completely different vision of reality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So television is not reflecting the real world.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it makes you believe somehow that murder and crime and violence is the way of life.
[SPEAKER_03]: So therefore, studies
[SPEAKER_03]: which is not anymore possible because TV is everywhere, but studies that show the difference after the introduction of television that was done in remote areas of Canada, in South Africa and in Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has shown that following the years after introduction of television, because of the violent contents of many of the broadcasts,
[SPEAKER_03]: crime rate has increased aggressiveness as verbal aggressiveness and physical aggressiveness as something double or triple.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's nobody contest those results but nobody pays attention because the financial lobbies are so strong and it's a big mistake because in fact violence, people think the violent will attract more audience.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has been shown that also it's not true.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a study, they took a violent thriller, which is a well-done story, and they took out all the 20 most violent episodes out of the film.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they left the storyline, which was very entertaining.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they run that to 50 students, one with the violent content, one with the violent content taken out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And actually, the non-violent edited thriller, which was still very engaging, the rating of 50 students was better.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's a mistake also to think that because of violence, you're going to attract attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: And most of the blockbuster movies are often very human ones that really people enjoy because it's so moving and it gives a good idea of human being.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I think not only it's very mean for the lobbyists to impose those violent images knowing the consequences for the children, but it's also a wrong bet because in fact people do naturally prefer movies that are more inspiring, that violent movies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your eminence and venerable, thank you so much for having us and please enjoy your stay in Hong Kong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, thank you for my side.